[
    {
        "question": "The Samyukta Maharashtra Samiti succeeded in making Pandit Nehru aware of the conditions as well as of the ...... of the Marathi speaking people.",
        "options": [
            "Sentiments",
            "Leadership",
            "Feelings",
            "Ideals"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Elections results made it clear that the voters were against ...... state and in favour of Samyukta Maharashtra.",
        "options": [
            "Lingual",
            "Bilingual"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1956, as per the amendment of the Constitution ...... was included in it.",
        "options": [
            "Article 371 (2)",
            "Article 371 (1)",
            "Article 370 (1)",
            "Article 370 (2)"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "When it was clear that ...... will not be included in Maharashtra at that time there arouse a huge public agitation.",
        "options": [
            "Pune",
            "Nagpur",
            "Kolhapur",
            "Mumbai"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "In ...... the parliament passed the Mumbai Reorganisation Act.",
        "options": [
            "November 1957",
            "April 1960",
            "November 1956",
            "April 1959"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "To accelerate the struggle for the Samyukta Maharashtra movement on 21 November 1955 decision of ……… day strike was taken.",
        "options": [
            "One",
            "Two",
            "Three",
            "Five"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "The issue of the demand of the Marathi speaking people started becoming ………",
        "options": [
            "Easier",
            "Simple",
            "Complicated",
            "Difficult"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "A huge meeting was held on ………. maidan in Mumbai.",
        "options": [
            "Gwalior",
            "Kamgar",
            "Tilak",
            "Keshavrao"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "A grand march led by Senapati Bapat was taken to ………. .",
        "options": [
            "Mantralaya",
            "Vidhan Parishad",
            "Vidhan Sabha",
            "Lok Sabha"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The struggle of ……….. speaking people for formation of Maharashtra with Mumbai.",
        "options": [
            "Marathi",
            "Hindu",
            "Gujarati",
            "Muslim"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "……… organized rallies to protest against the report of JVP committee.",
        "options": [
            "Sane Guruji",
            "P. K. Atre",
            "Senapati Bapat",
            "Prabodhan Thackeray"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Yashwantrao Chavan accepted the responsibility as first Chief Minister of ......",
        "options": [
            "Gujarat",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Kerala",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "On 6 February 1956, a meeting was conducted under the chairmanship of Keshavrao Jedhe at Tilak Smarak Mandir in ......",
        "options": [
            "Pune",
            "Nagpur",
            "Mumbai",
            "Wai"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Commission for Reconstruction of states advocated for creation of ...... Mumbai state",
        "options": [
            "Multilingual",
            "Bilingual"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "……… got passed the proposal of Samyukta Maharashtra with Mumbai in the Mumbai Municipal corporation.",
        "options": [
            "Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "S. K. Dar",
            "Lokmanya Tilak",
            "Acharya Atre"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "The samyukta Maharashtra samiti succeeded in making ...... aware of the conditions as well as the sentiments of the Marathi speaking people.",
        "options": [
            "Pandit Nehru",
            "Gandhiji",
            "Lokmanya Tilak",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "S. M. Joshi proposed a resolution that samyukta Maharashtra with Mumbai and ...... should be exerted.",
        "options": [
            "Sangli",
            "Vidarbha",
            "Nagpur",
            "Bhandara"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "……… President of the congress supported the samyukta Maharashtra movement.",
        "options": [
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Indira Gandhi",
            "Hansaben Mehta",
            "Rani Laxmibai"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "In memory of the ……… sons of Maharashtra who became martyr for formation of Samyukta Maharashtra, the ‘Hutatma Smarak’ was erected.",
        "options": [
            "290",
            "106",
            "109",
            "189"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Maharashtra state was formed on ………..",
        "options": [
            "5th May 1960",
            "1st May 1960",
            "6th May 1960",
            "8th May 1960"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Government of India appointed a commission for Reconstruction of states on 29 December 1953, under the chairmanship of Justice ……….",
        "options": [
            "Fazal Ali",
            "S. K. Dar",
            "Acharya Atre",
            "Shankarrao Dev"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "……… established Dar commission for forming linguistic province",
        "options": [
            "Morarji Desai",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
            "Yashwantrao Chavan"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "During that time Senapati Bapat organized ...... for the awakening of people.",
        "options": [
            "Procession",
            "Rallies",
            "Protest",
            "Agitation"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Maharashtra movement the role of ...... was important.",
        "options": [
            "Television",
            "Newspapers",
            "Radio",
            "Internet"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    }
]